<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The opinion of Peter Turner Doct: in physicke, concerning amulets or plague cakes whereof perhaps some holde too much, and some too little.</title>
            <author>Turner, Peter, 1542-1614.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24343</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102037</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837838</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837838</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2184</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14038)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2184)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1040:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The opinion of Peter Turner Doct: in physicke, concerning amulets or plague cakes whereof perhaps some holde too much, and some too little.</title>
                  <author>Turner, Peter, 1542-1614.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Read] for Edward Blount,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Print faded and show-through; title page marked and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2184:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 134 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:2184:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 134 -->
            <p>THE OPINION OF PETER TVRNER <hi>DOCT: IN PHYSICKE, CONCER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING</hi> AMVLETS OR PLAGVE <hi>CAKES, WHEREOF PERHAPS</hi> ſome holde too much, and <hi>ſome too little.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward Blount.</hi> 1603. <add>beinge the yeare of the great plague</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2184:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 135 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:2184:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 135 -->
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>The opinion of</hi> Peter Turner Docter in Phiſicke, concerning <hi>Amulets or Plague cakes; whereof</hi> perhaps ſome holde too much, and ſome too little.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is very true gentle Reader, that <hi>Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke, Orpiment,</hi> Sublimate <hi>praecipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, Quick-ſiluer, Todes</hi> and <hi>Adders,</hi> are in ſome ſorte rancke and deadlye poyſons in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree. For day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experience might teach it, though no learned writer had once men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned it. But it followeth not therefore that there is no vſe of them in Phiſick or curing of diſeaſes. For, to omit all the probable arguments taken from ſweete Kirnels in bitter ſhels, precious Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds in the middeſt of courſe ſtones, and Pearles in baſe Oyſters, alledged both by Philoſophers
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2184:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 136 -->and Phiſitians, to prooue that in moſt poyſoned ſubiects may be the nobleſt remedies, it is euident by the practiſe both of learned and vnlearned, that they are often vſed both inwardly and outwardly. My ſelfe I haue diuers times and yet not without the warrant of good Authors both old and new, cured ſundry extreame coughes and impoſtuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lungs with the fume of <hi>Orpiment</hi> adminiſtred by the mouth. My ſelfe alſo had the rebellious rootes of a Wen (after I had vſed <hi>Sublimate</hi> and <hi>Praecipitate,</hi> in vaine) well taken away with <hi>Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick.</hi> The place of the Wen being cloſe by the ridge bone ouer-againſt the hart. I haue alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times both giuen, and ſeene giuen <hi>Crude Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie,</hi> that is Quickſiluer vnto children for the wormes, and that with good ſucceſſe. As for <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limate</hi> and <hi>Praecipitate,</hi> I referre me to any man of any reading or experience, whether they bee not dayly and vſually adminiſtred both within and without, and that with good ſucceſſe, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally being brought as chymicall writers call it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Turbittes: <hi>Toades</hi> dried and giuen in powder inwardly prouoake vrine exceedingly, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly applyed they ſtay bleeding moſt miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, and drawe forth the matter of the plague into themſelues, without breaking of the parties skin, or any other harme. Concerning <hi>Adders,</hi> who knoweth not that from them the <hi>Triacles</hi> haue their names in Greeke, becauſe they are the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2184:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 136 -->Baſis or moſt principall ingredient whereof they are compounded. Now if the fume of <hi>Orpiment</hi> may be taken inwardly, and the ſubſtance of <hi>Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> applyed to Vlcers and raw wounds, wherein is as much danger of poyſoning as by ſwallowing of it, as may appeare by the ſpeedie death of wilde beaſts vpon the leaſt raiſing of their skinnes with Arrow-heads dipped in <hi>Toxicum</hi> and ſuch like poyſons: I know no cauſe why a man ſhould be afraide to weare them (eſpecially incloſed in ſilke) vpon the whole skin. Neither how they can be perpetually oppoſite to mans nature. Nay if that be a true and ſufficient definition of poyſon <hi>At no time to agree with nature.</hi> I ſee not how theſe things may ſimply be called poyſons, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times and in ſome caſes as hath bin ſhewed agree with nature as well as a man would wiſh. As for that point that ſomtimes they bliſter the skin, and cauſe angry wheales or pumples to ariſe, ſeeing that inconuenience may be both eaſily preuented and as eaſily cured, &amp; commeth onely but by the wearers default it needeth not to terriſie any man from the vſing of them. For if the wearer of theſe Amulets or plague cakes, aſſoone as they begin to ſweat, either take away the Cake, or put linnen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough betweene it &amp; the skin, or ſew it in thicker ſtuffe, or anoint the place with oyle or any vnctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſe thing, they may be free enough from that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2184:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 137 -->
And if aſſoone as it beginneth to breede any itching, or raiſe any pimple, they remooue the cake for a day or two, and annoint the place with a little creame or <hi>Vnguentum album Camphoratum,</hi> they ſhall not neede to complaine of any deepe or foule holes or vlcerations. And yet it may be a queſtion worth the conſidering, whether to haue ſuch things ariſe, be not rather a benefit where they appeare, then a harme. For ſeeing the ſame effect or accident hapneth not to all that weare them, nor to all that ſweate, it may ſeeme that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they are ſubiect to ſuch bliſterings in whome there is ſome venemous matter, which nature by the helpe of the medicine laboureth to expell. And as worthy the conſideration it is, now we talke of bliſtering and corroding, to call to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, how <hi>Garleeke, Muſtart,</hi> and <hi>Roſa ſolis,</hi> the hearbe, being greatbliſterers of the skinne, are not for that condemned for poyſons, nor refuſed to be taken into the ſtomach. The ioyce of a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon will graue vpon a knife as well as <hi>Aqua fortis</hi> or ſtrong water, and yet who euer had any harme by taking of it inwardly. To bliſter therefore or corrode the skinne, is not a ſufficient argument to proue a thing a poyſon. It is alſo very euident both by experience and reaſon, that things out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly applyed haue action, and worke into the body by communicating their ſpirituall qualities (as I may call them) to the ſpirites of our bodyes,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2184:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 137 -->by the meanes of the warmth that openeth our pores, and rarefying the ſubtill parts of the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, is the cauſe of a reciprocate action and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as may appeare by purging ſimples and plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. And herevpon, notwithſtanding what hath beene aboue ſaide, and perhaps not ſufficiently wayed, it may ſeeme ſtrange to ſome how <hi>Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> &amp; ſuch like ſtrong poyſons, hauing ſo ſtrong poyſoning ſpirits, ſhould not alſo poyſon our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits whereſoeuer they meete. For the better ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of ſuch as are not carryed away with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer praeiudice, and are capeable of theſe matters, this is in briefe my anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arſenick</hi> and <hi>Orpiment</hi> are no wayes poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus or hurtfull to nature, but by their corroſiuenes or fretting qualities: otherwiſe they are as good, if not better, both preſeruatiues and curers as any other moſt in vſe: and therefore ſo long as they are kept from corroding or fretting, they can doe no harme, but may doe much good in that kinde, which they reſpect: That is to ſay, in all <hi>Arſenicall</hi> diſeaſes, as the Plague, the Pluriſie, <hi>Noli me tange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> Canckers and Fiſtulas, and all of that kinde. If thou deſire this to be confirmed vnto thee by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample or experience, to wit, that they may be kept from corroding: Beholde the Mounte-bankes or Quackſaluers of Germany and Italy, who before they play their parts before the people, drinke firſt in their lodgings for that purpoſe halfe a pinte or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2184:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 138 -->more of Sallat-oyle, and then comming to their ſtage, take inwardly in all mens ſight incredible quantities of theſe poiſons, and then taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing after them but their Triacles which they haue to ſell, make their beholders beleeue that by them they be preſerued from all harme. (Of this thou mayeſt ſee more at large in <hi>Mathiolus</hi> in his Commentaries vpon <hi>Dioſcorides</hi>) whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth as I ſaide before, that they may be kept from fretting or corroding of the inwarde parts, which granted, it followeth that the like may be done outwardly, and ſo be worne ſafely vpon the bare skin, notwithſtanding their corroſiue quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be no wayes taken away. But if they may be cleane taken away, as all that are well practiſed in chimicall praeparations do affirme, I ſee no reaſon why they ſhould be ſo feared, eſpecially to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied outwardly. And why ſhould it not be as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to remooue the corroſiue qualities of mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals from their bodies, as well as to remooue the burning quality of <hi>Aron</hi> rootes, called in Engliſh <hi>Starch-worte,</hi> or <hi>Wake-Robin</hi> from them, which I haue ſeene done, &amp; then as pleaſant bread made of them as of any other graine: or as well as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue the bitterneſſe of the gall of an Oxe, which my ſelfe haue done, and brought it to be as ſweete as the ioyce of Liquorice, and then adminiſtred it with good ſucceſſe in the yellow Iaundiſſe. But ſuppoſe that this were impoſſible: why may there
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2184:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 138 -->not be as ſure a way to correct that qualitie by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall meanes as there is to correct the offending qualities of <hi>Scammony, Agarick, Helleborus, Euphor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium</hi> and ſuch like by their like, that is by Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitables? Is it abſurd, nay is there not great proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie to thinke that God hath in nature appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted minerall <hi>Alexipharmaca</hi> praeſeruatiues or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies againſt the greateſt poiſons in that kinde, when we ſee that in vegitables he hath in his great mercy and prouidence created an <hi>Antithora</hi> for a <hi>Thora,</hi> and an <hi>Antieuphorbium</hi> for <hi>Euphorbium,</hi> I thinke not. And if neede were I can name ſome, but that ſuch ſecrets ought alwayes to remaine with them that know them. Now if any man not ſatiſfied with that which hath beene ſaide, obiect yet farther, that I haue proued but the halfe of that which they expected. That is, that theſe Amulets may be ſafly worne without any harme, not ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the other more neceſſary part, that they may do any good. For ſatisfying all ſuch, (although there is enough ſaid to thoſe that hold them dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, which is the queſtion now in controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,) I will farther yet briefly tell you my opinion of that point alſo, vpon that ſmall knowledge (yet dearly bought) which I imagine I haue in chimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call matters, partly by my own experience, &amp; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by reading of the profeſſors of that arte: I aſſure my ſelfe that there is in theſe minerals which the Alchimiſts cal their ſpirits good ſtore of gold, or to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2184:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 139 -->ſpeake a little plainer of the ſpirits of golde: and from thence in my opinion it hath that incredible and admirable operation in preſeruing of our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits from infection. For the better confirmation of this my ſuppoſition, to wit, that minerall ſpirits are not without parte of the mettals from which they come; If you will demaund of the refiners or meltars downe of mettals, what the reaſon is why many times they cannot get the golde or other mettals which they know to be in their Ores or Owres, they will anſwer you that the aboundance of the wilde ſpirites that are in them when they bring them to the blaſt, carry away all the metall with them, which they doe by eating of them vp as ſtrong waters vſe to doe. But if thou haddeſt rather heare what the learneder ſorte that deale with ſuch things holde of theſe matters. Then read what is written in a treatiſe of <hi>Arſenick</hi> by <hi>Theopraſtus Paracelſus,</hi> who was abſolutly the moſt learnedſt chimicall writer and worker that euer wrote: And if thou haſt any inſight in this kind of Philoſophie, whereby to vnderſtand him, he will ſatiſfie thee of the natures of theſe things to the full. As for the authorities of ſuch Phiſitians or Philoſophers which are not acquainted neither with the chymicall theory nor practiſe, I holde their cenſures as inſufficient, for want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thoſe things which they diſlike: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how many ſoeuer they be in number, ſo long
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2184:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 139 -->as they vnderſtand not what they reprehend, it maketh no great matter: and yet if this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie were to be debated by authorities, my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſhould not be leſſe aſſiſted then any others. But ſeeing it would be both tedious and needleſſe for the readers to be troubled with ſuch allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I wil not take that courſe at this time, in which my intent is only to let them know what my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and practiſe is of theſe things. Yet leaſt it might be thought that I haue none but poore <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racelſus</hi> on my ſide, I will tranſlate for them that vnderſtand no Lattin, a fewe lines concerning theſe Amulets and Plague cakes, out of a little Treatiſe of the Plague of <hi>Iohannis Piſtorius</hi> a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Phiſition of <hi>Germanie;</hi> his wordes are theſe. <hi>Many</hi> Italian <hi>Phiſitions are of that opinion, that there was neuer a more excellent thing (ſpeaking of theſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulets) graunted to mortall men by God, to preſerue them from the Plague, and therefore call it a diuine me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine inuented by God, and take it vpon their oathes that neuer any fell ſicke that wore them, and ſo much the more and the better I like of them, ſaith</hi> Piſtorius, <hi>becauſe their notable profit or vertue is confirmed by experience and made manifeſt to the ſenſes,</hi> and a few lines after he ſaith further. <hi>And ſo much the more am I mooued to like of them, becauſe in the yeare</hi> 64. <hi>in</hi> Zurick, <hi>I neuer knew any amongst a great many that wore them to get any harme by them, or dye of the Plague, notwithſtanding the great conuerſation that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2184:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 140 -->the ſound had with the ſicke, according to the cuſtome of that place. And at</hi> Baſill <hi>the like was obſerued.</hi> As theſe things (gentle reader) moued the foreſaid <hi>Piſtorius</hi> to allowe and preſcribe theſe Amulets to his patients, ſo haue the ſame (together with my owne long obſeruations) done the like with me, and ſo hauing as I promiſed brieflie, ſet downe my opinion, I commit thee to the head Phyſition, who ſend thee health both of ſoule and body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maledictus qui ponit carnem brachium ſuum:</hi> that is in effect; Accurſed be he that putteth his whole confidence in ſecondary meanes, for it is neither hearbe nor ſalue, nor any thing els that healeth, but onely the bleſſing of the head Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And herevpon it may fall out ſometimes that they who commit ſuperſtition or Idolatrie (as I may cal it) in wearing of theſe Amulets, may now and then notwithſtanding miſcarry, but it were pittie for that cauſe to derogate from the credite of ſo noble and generall a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, for a few perticular inſtances.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2184:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 140 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
